<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologetick for the sequestred clergie of the Church of England. Disclaiming and detesting the late unnatural, presumptuous, unparallel'd and antichristian proceedings, against the honor and life of the best of Kings, our most dear and dread sovereign Lord and King, St Charls the martyr. / Communicated in a letter to a religious and loial gentleman, his honored friend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E554_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75493)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E554[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologetick for the sequestred clergie of the Church of England. Disclaiming and detesting the late unnatural, presumptuous, unparallel'd and antichristian proceedings, against the honor and life of the best of Kings, our most dear and dread sovereign Lord and King, St Charls the martyr. / Communicated in a letter to a religious and loial gentleman, his honored friend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at New-Munster [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year of confusion [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false. Actual place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May.7.1649".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGETICK FOR THE SEQUESTRED CLERGIE OF THE Church of England. Diſclaiming and deteſting the late Unnatural, Preſumptuous, Unparallel'd and Antichriſtian Proceedings, againſt the Honor and Life of the Beſt of Kings, Our moſt Dear and Dread Sovereign Lord and King, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> CHARLS the MARTYR. Communicated in a Letter to a Religious and Loial Gentleman, his Honored Friend.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Crown is fallen from our head: Wo unto us that wee have ſinned.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lament. 5.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>O my Soul, com not thou into their ſecret: unto their AS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEMBLIE mine Honor bee not thou united.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 49.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>In reos Majeſtatis &amp; publicos hoſtes omnis homo miles eſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertull. Apol. parag.</hi> 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>New-Munſter</hi> in the year of <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:165082:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165082:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGETICK FOR THE SEQUESTRED CLERGIE OF THE Church of England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He late unparallel'd, preſumptuous, unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Antichriſtian Proceedings againſt the Honor and Life of the <hi>Beſt of Kings,</hi> our moſt Dear and Gracious Sovereign, by a Pretended-Legal Trial, Sentence and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Him, by incompetent, intereſſed, and armed Judges, without either Precedent, Law, Reaſon or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, at which <hi>the ears of everie one that beareth it do tingle,</hi> have not unjuſtly begot your indignation againſt, and deteſtation of, ſo high and inſolent a villanie, as was never acted before by the worſt of men, nor infuſed by the Prince of Divels.</p>
            <p>The tranſcendencie of this horrid work of darkneſs, this Maſter-piece of Hell, if wee except the Murther of the Son of God, (which was ſo neerly parallel'd by this, that wee could not but, with a juſt reflexion on it, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the diſpoſition of the Divine Providence, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Crucifixion of our Bleſſed Saviour recorded by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165082:3"/>Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> for the Proper Leſſon of that fatal Daie of the Martyrdom of our Juſt and Pious Prince) hath ſo far out-gon the Tragick phancies of the moſt ingenious witts in Crueltie and Malice; and withall, ſo far Eclipſed the Glorie of our Iſraël, heretofore famous and renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among the Nations, admired by our Friends, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by our Enemies; but now the juſt deriſion of the World, and out-caſt of the People; that wee cannot but look upon this Kingdom, or rather this <hi>Aceldama,</hi> with the ſaddeſt eie of compaſſionate affection and ſorrow, as once our <hi>Bleſſed Lord and Maſter</hi> did upon his ſomtime Darling <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Nor, indeed, will grief allow us to ſpeak out, what horrid conſequences have, in the anguiſh of our ſouls deeply afflicted with the contemplation of the eternal ruin of our Name, our Place, and our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, been ſadly repreſented to our thoughts. So true is that common ſaying, <hi>Ingentes ſtupent,</hi> that wee can ſcarce finde breath enough to ſaie with the Prophet <hi>Jeremie, O that our head were waters, and our eies fountains of tears!</hi> But are forced to break off with <hi>our Bleſſed Saviour</hi> (beholding and weeping over <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>) in His moſt pathetical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation and expreſſions, <hi>O, if thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy daie, the things which belong unto thy peace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SIR! Wee are confident, your deteſtation and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of this impious Parricide (beyond the worſt of <hi>Nero</hi>'s cruelties) hath not ſo far ſurprized and invaded your Charitie, (though it hath the bowels of the Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Nations) as to impute ſo great a guilt to all the Kingdom; wherein the Righteous Judg of all the earth and that's our higheſt comfort) well knoweth how to diſtinguiſh, and to laie this curſed Brat at the true Father's dore. And you may believ it, <hi>Sir,</hi> the characters of Humanitie are not ſo defaced, nor the impreſſions of Chriſtianitie ſo blotted out among us, but that you are ſeconded by Thouſands, who have not worſhipped the <hi>Golden Calvs,</hi> nor bow'd their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> in your juſt Anathema upon the curſed Authors of this Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the Heirs apparent of Damnation.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165082:3"/>
            <p>But ſomwhat more you think requir'd of us, of men of <hi>our Profeſſion,</hi> then an implicit ſilent Deteſtation. And <hi>our Calling</hi> ſeemeth to urge an abſolute neceſſitie upon us (leſt ſilence bee interpreted Conſent) to clear our Credit, Conſcience and Religion (the three great intereſts of all Chriſtians, and ſpecially Divines) by ſom Publick Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our Judgment concerning the late barbarous and unheard of Practiſes againſt <hi>our moſt Pious, Constant, Chriſtian King; the Light of our Iſräel, the Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, SIR, if wee had not that to ſaie by waie of Plea and Vindication of our Silence, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we hope will bee eſteemed rational and juſt by all intelligent and Loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſouls (for wee are not verie careful to pleaſ others) wee ſhould not dare to look for mercie, either from God or Man; but verie willingly expoſe our ſelvs as fit objects to the rage &amp; malice of our moſt implacable and bitter enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Wee cannot but with all thankfulneſs and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion acknowledg the manie great and tranſcendent bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings wee enjoi'd, among, if not above, the other Subjects under the happie Reign of his moſt glorious Majeſtie. Wee cannot but confeſs His high merits of us; whom not onely the common Obligations of the Oath of God, and our Natural Allegiance, but the due conſideration of His undeſerved reſpects and honors beſtowed upon our particular Profeſſion and Prieſtlie Function muſt eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indear unto us. And wee had been the moſt unworthie creatures upon Earth, had wee prooved <hi>Deſertores Fidei,</hi> had wee faltered in our Faith and Loialtie to Him, whom the Church muſt ever honor as her moſt glorious Patron and Protector: and, which is the higheſt elevation of His Love, (ſo neer was his to God's upon the Croſs) beyond all <hi>Conſtantine's, Theodoſius's,</hi> or <hi>Valentinian's,</hi> the moſt in. vincible Champion and Martyr for Her. Who, when Hee ſaw all waies of doing good, of improoving His af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Pietie to Her, barr'd up and utterly precluded by a religious Sacrilege, willingly laid down His Life for Her redemption; And, in imitation of the bleſſed JESUS,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165082:4"/>acted what Hee ſaid, <hi>If you ſeek Mee, let theſe go their waie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The contemplation of the glorious exceſſes of His tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Charitie and Devotion (for, <hi>Hee loved our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Zeal of God's Houſ had eaten him up</hi>) not onely giveth new Arguments for our deſign'd <hi>Apologetick,</hi> for clearing up the miſts now caſt upon us, by reaſon of our Silence in this Cauſ, but alſo ſupplieth us with rich grounds and materials for a <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> to the eternal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of His moſt pretious Memorie: But here wee are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with ſo much light, and ſuch tranſcendent beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of perfection in all the paſſages of His bleſſed Life and glorious Martyrdom, that all wee can conceiv or ſaie of Him would com as ſhort of His incomparable merits, as doth a Peeble of a Diamond, a Candle of the glories of the Sun, or our unworthie pen of His victorious and Seraphick quil. Wee cannot add a grain of honor to His glories, of which Hee is as full, as the eternitie of Heaven, in the fruition of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>God</hi> can make Him. Where Hee hath exchang'd His Crown of <hi>Thorns</hi> for one far more illuſtrious of <hi>Stars;</hi> and where His Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which was kindled here to verie high and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie proportions, hath now attein'd her ultimate perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and burneth with ever-living flames.</p>
            <p>The influence whereof, wee cannot doubt, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate the Clouds of black conſtructions, which threaten a ſtorm to our <hi>Reputation</hi> and our <hi>Conſcience;</hi> The <hi>One</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted with the engine of Falſhood, that wee dare not now in Perſecution own the Truth of that Doctrine, which, according to the example of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Catholick Clergie, wee profeſſed in our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie: The <hi>Other</hi> undermined with the bitter Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of our inſulting Enemies, who triumph over us with cruel <hi>Quaere's;</hi> Where are the great Pretenders for the King? where is the Roial Partie? (wee take it for <hi>Their ſcorn,</hi> but 'tis <hi>Our glorie</hi>) where they for whom Hee ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured Life and Crown? Not one that durſt appear, or ſhew his head in vindication of Him: Not one ſtood
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165082:4"/>in the gap to make up the breach, to mantein His Honor, Crown, or Life.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Pudet haec opprobria nobie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wee cannot but deplore our ſad condition, thus load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with unjuſt aſperſions. Theſe make ſuch deep impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on our ſouls, that we cannot but look upon them as an intollerable addition to our manie Sufferings; which, beeing aggravated to the higheſt pitch by theſe foul mouths, diſcover too much acquaintance and familiaritie with Hell, to bee believed by anie who have thoughts of Heaven. And, if we may obtein a little patience of pious and judicious Chriſtians, wee doubt not, wee ſhall give ſuch ſatisfaction as ſhall wipe off the deepeſt ſtains of Calumnie; and give in moſt clear evidence to all the world (whoſe Charitie wee beg not to impute ſo great a guilt to our Tribe and Profeſſion) that, as wee can, in the integritie of our ſouls, waſh our hands from having anie agencie in anie Scene of this accurſed Tragedie, ſo wee do abominate and deteſt the fatal Cloſe and Epilogue thereof; as beeing a moſt deſtructive Principle and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which muſt neceſſarily conclude (without the interpoſition of God's infinite and miraculous mercie) in the inevitable period and ruin of our Religion, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, Honor, Law, Libertie, Life, and whatſoever is moſt ſacred and dear to God and Man. All which, as it were the higheſt ingratitude not to acknowledg them to bee concentred and bound up in Him, to have been man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined and propagated by His gracious hand, and to have <hi>lived</hi> with Him, ſo wee cannot but now look upon as <hi>dead</hi> with Him, and <hi>buried</hi> in an eternal grave of infamie and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Which grave as it was not digg'd by us by anie actual concurrence or unworthie compliances, nor otherwiſe then as wee are involved and concluded in the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a finful people, now <hi>white unto the harveſt,</hi> and ripe for the fickle of Divine Vengeance; ſo the prevention of it beeing endeavored by us, as far as lawfully wee might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165082:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165082:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165082:6"/>in our vocation, wee are confident the blame and guilt of the ſucceeding miſeries and miſchiefs cannot bee juſtly charged upon us; <hi>who, though wee live among them, are not of them,</hi> but, like the righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> through the neceſſitie of our cohabitation in <hi>this Sodom,</hi> are grieved with the preſumptuous converſation of theſe Heaven-daring miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants.</p>
            <p>Who, that they might ſecurely, uncontrol'd, walk on in the forbidden paths of higheſt Treaſon, againſt the <hi>Lord Himſelf,</hi> &amp; <hi>His Annointed,</hi> took order for the ſtopping of our mouths, who could not ſpeak <hi>the Language of the Beaſt,</hi> nor frame our tongues to their new <hi>Shibboleth</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Leagues,</hi> of <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Covenants. Haec Lerna malorum.</hi> This was the fountain of our miſeries, whence all thoſe bitter ſtreams have iſſued, with which the <hi>Loial Clergie</hi> of this Church, for ſeven yeers paſt, have mingled both their drink and tears. This the occaſion of that curſed <hi>Deluge,</hi> which, in flat oppoſition to that other ſent by God for the drowning of <hi>a ſinful World,</hi> hath overwhelmed <hi>Noah,</hi> and the <hi>Ark,</hi> and ſaved <hi>the poſteritie of Cain.</hi> This was that <hi>Trojan Horſ,</hi> which uſher'd in thoſe armed cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, which, under the ſpecious ſhews of <hi>Reformation, and ſetting up the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> have given the greateſt blow to His Religion, undermined the Foundations of Chriſtianitie, and level'd the Throne of Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie with the plough-ſhares and the mattocks of the earth.</p>
            <p>Thus, SIR, wee have at laſt diſcours'd our ſelvs up to the bitter ſprings of <hi>Meribah;</hi> the ſource of all our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; the Mother or the Nurſe of theſe confuſions; and, in a word, the <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of this late flouriſhing, now miſerably ruin'd Church and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Our utter deteſtation whereof, for wee cannot caſt our eies upon it, but as upon ſom blazing Star, or prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Comet, portending dire effects of blood and death to us and Chriſtian Religion, (which never own'd the Principles on foot againſt the Higheſt Powers for anie Articles of Her Faith) give's clear light and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165082:6"/>of our Innocence, which hath not onely been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by manie of our Brethen, in their Publick Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Churche's judgment in the points of Non-Reſiſtance and Allegiance, but alſo ſealed with the Blood of ſom, and with the Sufferings of all.</p>
            <p>Theſe two, 1 The Proteſtations of our Judgment, and 2 The manie Sufferings endured by us, in the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous proſecution of <hi>This Cauſe,</hi> had been enough to have convinced anie of our Uprightneſs and Integritie; if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had learn'd but ſo much Charitie, as the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian Religion dictate to as or but ſo much Humanitie as is taught them by the dimmer Light of Nature.</p>
            <p>But truly, SIR, the importunate aſperſions of our Enemies force us to a ſeeming neglect of all Humilitie, and a forgetfulneſs of Modeſtie. And wee muſt, by waie of juſt Apologie, but without all arrogance and ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, ſaie with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul, If wee are fools in glorying, they have compelled us,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.11.</p>
            <p>And here wee are encompaſſed with a Cloud of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: and the eminent Examples of the Saints, the Fore-runners of our Faith, will not onely excuſe but pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize this our juſt Defenſe, and now neceſſitated boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Looking unto</hi> JESUS, <hi>the Author and Finiſher of our Faith; who, for the glorie that was ſet before Him, endured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quot vulnera tot ora:</hi> Our conſtant courſe of ſufferings proclaims at once our Judgment and our Innocence. 'Tis true, indeed, wee have not attained to that high Heroïck pitch of the Primitive Martyrs; of whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (by waie of Prophecie, with reſpect to them that were to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after, no leſs then of Hiſtorie, referring unto them that went before) ſpeaketh thoſe glorious exceſſes of Faith, and Charitie, and Zeal. <hi>They ſtopped the mouths of Lions.</hi> So did theſe: For wee know the old word was, <hi>Chriſtianes ad Leonem. Som were tortured, not accepting deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance:</hi> It was a crime with them to bee but <hi>Libellatici:</hi> and they contemn'd their lives that they might preſerv
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165082:7"/>their ſoul and honor, free from the guilt of ſin, nay from miſpriſion. <hi>Others had trials, of cruel mockings and ſcourgings: yea moreover of ſtripes and impriſonment.</hi> Not was this much to them, who well remembred that it behoved them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the High-Prieſt of our Profeſſion, <hi>who was</hi> thus <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by ſufferings. They were</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
               <hi>Stoned, they were</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">2</hi> 
               <hi>Sawn aſunder, were</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">3</hi> 
               <hi>Tempted, were</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">4</hi> 
               <hi>Slain with the Sword.</hi> So was the Proto-martyr <hi rend="sup">1.</hi> St <hi>Stephan,</hi> the Prophet <hi rend="sup">2.</hi> 
               <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Patriarch <hi rend="sup">3.</hi> 
               <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi rend="sup">4.</hi> 
               <hi>Zachariah</hi> the Prieſt, the Father of the Baptiſt. <hi>They wandered about in ſheep-skins, and goat-skins: beeing deſtitute, afflicted, tormented.</hi> Their glories were <hi>within,</hi> their garments mean and ſuitable to their habitations, <hi>For they wandered in deſerts and in moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and in dens and in caves of the earth. Of whom the world was not worthie.</hi> And wherefore this, <hi>quo oculo? For they had a reſpect unto the recompenſe of the reward: that they might receiv a glorious Reſurrection.</hi> And are theſe the prizes of our Sufferings? Theſe were enough to ſweeten bitterneſs it ſelf: to make them welcom Death, to hug the Croſs, to embrace the Flames. Indeed, wee have not drunk ſo deep as they in the bitter Cup of Gall and Vineger. Wee dare not ſaie, Our Sufferings equal Theirs, in the degrees or qualitie of torments. They were more noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded us; triumphing in their Chariots of Fire; dallying with Lions and the cruel beaſts, leſs cruel then their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Maſters; ſinging upon the Gridirons and Racks of exquiſite and new-invented Tortures; tiring the malice of inhumane Butchers with an undanted Chriſtian reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, with a victorious Faith and Patience; ſpitting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance in the face of Crueltie, pregnant with Heathen wit, and arm'd with power. Theſe were the great exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of thoſe Worthies, who knew no other Arms but theſe (beſides their Praiers and Tears) to fight with and to conquer a world of Tyrants and of Infidels. <hi>Theſe things</hi> did <hi>thoſe mightie men.</hi> Did: ſo wee ſaid; for ſure they were not counted Sufferings, which were thus court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and embraced by them. Such were the Leaders in the glorious Armie of the Martyrs. Nor have they wanted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165082:7"/>honorable followers in all the Ages of the Chriſtian Church. Who, though they did not wade ſo deep in the <hi>Red Sea of Blood,</hi> yet marched after in their <hi>Liveries</hi> of Stripes, of Bonds and Perſecutions; the leſſer <hi>marks of the Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, the Captain</hi> both of Suffering and <hi>Salvation.</hi> The difference of whoſe glorious reward, acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental perhaps, but not ſubſtantial, an <hi>Aureola</hi> to one, to one a <hi>Crown,</hi> will bee abundantly made up and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled in the bleſſed fellowſhip of Saints and Angels, and the eternal fruition of Chriſt and God; to the full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleting of the greateſt Hope, and the aſſurance given by S. <hi>Paul</hi> That <hi>the light afflictions which are but for a moment ſhall work,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (an Hyperbolical expreſſion for an Hyperbolical reward) <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glorie.</hi> Indeed, <hi>wee dare not compare our ſelvs to theſe, nor make our ſelvs of their member who were the glorie of their times.</hi> It will bee joie enough for us, if wee can ſaie</p>
            <q>— Sequimur Patres,—</q>
            <p>though wee bee forced to add</p>
            <q>—non paſſibue aequit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Shee did what ſhee could,</hi> was, to our comfort, compead a good Plea by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and juſtified in <hi>Marie Magdalen.</hi> Wee dare not, nay wee need not plead the rigor and intenſneſs of our Sufferings: for, bee they more or leſs, by Sword or Fire; by Death, or by beeing but Undon; <hi>Wee are acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted according to that which wee have, not that which wee have not.</hi> But, if anie queſtion the Juſtneſs of our Cauſe (a righteous Cauſe if ever anie) or doubt of the Intention and Preparation of our Souls, <hi>Quocunque Dens,</hi> to follow whither God ſhall pleaſ to call us, <hi>Wee ſpeak fooliſhly,</hi> but wee ſpeak it with S. <hi>Paul, Whereinſoever anie dare bee bold, wee dare bee hold alſo.</hi> Are they Chriſtians? even ſo are wee. Are they true Sons of the Church of England? even ſo are wee. Have they ſuffered for righteouſneſs ſake? even ſo have wee. <hi>Are they the Miniſters of Chriſt? (wee ſpeak as fools) wee are more. In Labers more abundant; in ſtripes above meaſure; in Priſons more froquent; in deaths oft. If wee muſt needs glorie, wee will glorie in the things which concern our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:165082:8"/>The Plunderings, Sequeſtrations, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Baniſhment, Death of thouſands, endured by us with ſo much Patience, Meekneſs, and Heroïck Courage; Our Conſtancie and Perſeverance in this fierie Trial; ſtill holding our Integritie, and bleſſing God, in the loſs of all, ſave Faith and a good Conſcience, are evidence enough to God and Man, that wee cannot but deteſt ſuch high impietie, which, ſtriking ſo immediatly at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Perſon of the King, <hi>God's Vicar</hi> upon Earth, will mediately bee found, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſtrike at God Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>But, becauſ the fouleſt Fiend ſomtime put's on the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Vizard; and the Prince of Darkneſs hath been often known to transform himſelf into an Angel of Light; the furious Donatiſts cried out of Perſecution, and, in a fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Zeal and mad Devotion, ventured upon ſwords and flames, pretending the Religion of a Holie Cauſe, (as here their younger Brethren did and do) to warrant their unjuſtifiable Actions; Groundleſs ſuſpitions may bee rais'd of us; our Innocencie may bee counted a Malefactor; and our verie Sufferings may ſuffer. But, if <hi>Cauſa non Paena facit Martyrem</hi> bee a truth and ever taken ſo to bee by men of all Perſwaſions and Profeſſions, wee ſhall not doubt to own our Sufferings, and juſtifie Our ſelvs and Them by the preſcription of a <hi>Righteous Cauſe.</hi> Indeed, wee cannot ſee by their <hi>New Lights,</hi> which ſeem to us more black then the <hi>Egyptian Darkneſs.</hi> Their <hi>Revelations</hi> are <hi>Obſcurities:</hi> and their <hi>Apocalypſ, Apocrypha.</hi> Wee dare not give our Faith to their Pretenſions; wee dare not truſt their Spirit without Trial; ſince wee have found it, to the woful diſturbance of Chriſtendom, run croſs and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorie to the Holie Faith, which was conſigned to the Catholick Church in the undoubted Records, and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible volumes of the Sacred Scripture; which, upon better and more certain grounds then the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> have the higheſt privilege and honor, as dictated by the Spirit of Truth, to bee unalterable. <hi>Wee know,</hi> ndeed, <hi>that God ſpake in them: as for theſe men wee know not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165082:8"/>whence they are.</hi> It is <hi>another Spirit</hi> they pretend: It is <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> whom they Preach: It is <hi>another GOD,</hi> whom they Adore. The Holie Spirit wee know: JESUS wee know: and GOD wee know: <hi>But who are theſe?</hi> If we may paſs a judgment by their works, (and Chriſt will warrant us by His, <hi>Ex fructibus, You ſhall know them by their fruits</hi>) They are not Sheep, but Wolvs; not Doves, but Vultures; not what they call themſelvs, the Meek, the Saints: They ſpeak their Father and his works they do, who was a Serpent; is a roaring Lion: who, having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged the higheſt Treaſon againſt his ſupreme Lord and Sovereign, the King of Heaven and Earth, not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged many of his fellow-ſubjects in that grand Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, but hath ever ſince made it his work to diſturb all Kingdoms but his own, (for there hee will endure <hi>nec priorem, nec parem</hi>) to ſet the world on fire, to raiſe up Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and to ſhake the verie foundations of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Order.</p>
            <p>But <hi>wee have not ſo learned Chriſt:</hi> nor can the Principles of Chriſtian Doctrine conſiſt with ſuch Unchriſtian Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. <hi>Wee ſpake openly to the world; wee ever taught in the Temple, whither the people alwaies reſort, and in ſecret have wee ſaid nothing. Ask not of us; Ask them that heard us, what wee have ſaid unto them; Behold, they know not what wee ſaid,</hi> S. <hi>Job.</hi> 18.20, 21. Firſt, wee appeal to God, and next, to them who knew <hi>the manner of our Life,</hi> and Doctrine, <hi>if they would teſtifie,</hi> that after that waie which they call <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancie</hi> (for ſo they miſ-call the Doctrine and Practiſe of our Chriſtian brethren) <hi>ſo worſhip wee the God of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſo have wee been taught, as the truth is in</hi> JESUS, <hi>to Fear</hi> GOD <hi>and the</hi> KING, <hi>and not to meddle with them that are given to Change;</hi> beeing aſſured by the Spirit of Truth, who cannot lie, That <hi>their deſtruction ſhall ariſe ſuddenly; and who kneweth the ruin of them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Knowing therfore this</hi> Truth and <hi>terror of the Lord,</hi> leſt wee ſhould incur the juſt reward of partaking in the ſins of other men (which wee have labored to prevent and hinder both by our Example and Diſcourſes) Wee do,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165082:9"/>in the Name of God, <hi>ad liberandas animas noſtras,</hi> to clear our ſouls of the Innocent blood of our Juſt and Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous PRINCE, <hi>Declare</hi> the late preſumptuous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt his Life and Honor to bee Jeſuitical and Antichriſtian; contrarie to the <hi>Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> and ever profeſſed by the Catholick Church of Chriſt, and, in ſpecial, by the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Wee acknowledg and declare to all the world, that the KING is <hi>ſolo Deo minor,</hi> as in the old Divinitie of <hi>Tertullian.</hi> That <hi>Sub-</hi> or <hi>Co-ordination</hi> deſtroie the eternal <hi>Miſhpat,</hi> the righteous Law of God, planted in Nature, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in the Holie Scriptures, for the abſolute, indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Supreme Dominon of God's Vicegerent, the Sacred Majeſtie of His Anointed. That Hee is not, by anie Law of God or Man, accomptable to his Subjects; no, not in the ſuppoſed caſe of male-adminiſtration: <hi>ſatis erit ut Deum exſpectet ultorem,</hi> was thought by the old Chriſtians a ſufficient thunder-bolt to keep Him in good order. That Hee hath no Superior upon Earth to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Jurisdiction over Him. That <hi>[Againſt Thee onely have I ſinned]</hi> could not bee truly ſaid by King <hi>David,</hi> upon any other conſideration, but His unqueſtionable Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption from all Humane Judicatories. That Hee is a King by Him alone, by whom Hee is a man: without all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal or Popular dependence. And that the Curſing of the King, but in our Thought; much more the ſlandering and reviling with our Tongue; much more the Depoſition and Dethroning; but, above all, the Taking of His Life is a Crime of deepeſt ſtain, and the higheſt breach of all the Laws of God and Men.</p>
            <p>Theſe, SIR, are no new receiv'd opinions of Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daie, or of this later Age; They antedate the Aera of Chriſtianitie, and are contemporarie with Nature: and it were eaſie work to fill whole volumes with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Names of our Fathers who lived and died in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation and mantenance of this Faith, which, now ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering under the odious Name of Malignancie, Court-Divinitie, and flattering of Princes, was the chief quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165082:9"/>of the world againſt us, to the diſhereſon of us in our temporal fortunes; and, which was far more grievous, to the eternal ruin of thoſe pretious ſouls for vvhich Chriſt died; vvhom, by the ſtopping of our mouths, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the Truth by the mouths of <hi>Ababs Prophets,</hi> ſubſtituted unduly and intruded, againſt all Law and Conſcience, into our Cures, it laie not in the power of our Chriſtian Charitie to ſave from the deep ingagement of the wrath of God upon them, here; nor, which is worſe, the entailing of an eternal curſe upon their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, and (without Repentance) upon their Souls.</p>
            <p>And now, SIR, what need of farther witneſſes of our Integritie and Innocence? what Reaſon can object or laie on us the imputation of ſo great a guilt? what could wee hope might poſſily prevail, when the engagement of our Fortunes, Lives and Souls, the beſt and deareſt pledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es wee could ſtake, could not procure that credit unto us, or mercie to themſelvs, as to divert them from thoſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid waies, which know no end but Hell and deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And with theſe onely wee could very well have ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our ſelvs in point of Conſcience, and have offered them to God for His acceptance. But more wee have to ſaie by waie of Plea, which like pack-thred and paper wee ſhall caſt into the bargain. And that upon this double conſideration. 1. Of the ſeeming Improbabilitie of the Attempting an Action of ſo extravagant a nature. 2. Of the Impoſſibilitie of good Succeſs, in caſe wee had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>firſt:</hi> what wiſe and honeſt man could ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally imagin, that ſuch unnatural, unheard of Thoughts could probably poſſeſs the hearts of anie, who had not firſt caſt off Humanitie and Reaſon, not to ſpeak of Conſcience and Religion? What <hi>Hazael</hi> would not ſtartle at the motion of ſo horrid, ſo unparallel'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie? and utter his deteſtation of it in his language, <hi>Am I a Dog?</hi> Wee preſumed the Actors in that fatal Tragedie would not bee ſo injurious to themſelvs as to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165082:10"/>take that for a fault in Us, Our Diſ-beleeving of ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious an Intention, the Beleeving of which to have been deliberated by anie, who had reſpect to Conſcience or Honor, was conceiv'd by us too great a breach of Chriſtian Charitie; which wee our ſelvs, though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent on the Stage, were loth to ſuffer to be ſo far invaded, notwithſtanding all that terrible pomp, and ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Preparations. Wee hoped better things from them who had aſſumed the Name of Reforming-Chriſtians, and of Saints: Nor durſt wee, while wee labored to bee innocent, by queſtioning or prejudging their innocence, endanger ours. But, indeed, beſide our <hi>Charitie,</hi> which, if S. <hi>Paul</hi> bee right, <hi>Thinketh no evil,</hi> which cannot bee it ſelf if but ſuſpitious, had wee not <hi>Reaſon</hi> too? Can Chriſtians bee induced to believ that Oaths and Vows and Proteſtations could bee no ſtronger ties upon the <hi>Saints,</hi> then Cords or Withs were in the hand of <hi>Sampſon?</hi> Or elſ that Regicide, a crying ſin, would bee a juſt ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to an incenſed God, for all our former faults and villanies? Or that the breaking of the <hi>Fift,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> Command, could make atonement for the breach of <hi>Nine?</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; O Sorcerie, how haſt thou broke forth to the ſupplanting of Chriſtianitie and Reaſon! <hi>Rebellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft,</hi> wee often <hi>heard</hi> before, wee <hi>ſee</hi> it now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But the <hi>ſecond,</hi> the Impoſſibilitie of good ſucceſs, in eaſe wee had appeared, vvhich vvas ſtrongly confirmed to us, whether wee reflected on 1 Our ſelvs, 2 The Managers of the Deſign, or 3 Others, both of their own Miniſters, and of the Loial, and Legal Clergie, was an effectual argument to us, and a ſufficient ground for our eternal ſilence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reflecting on Our ſelvs. For, ſuppoſing the Legal Clergie could have met, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with one mouth, with one minde, and prepared an uniform Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and back'd it with all the Arguments that Scripture, Reaſon, Law, or Conſcience could have ſuggeſted to us (which yet they took an order to prevent and actually
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165082:10"/>effected by the hotteſt perſecution that was ever ſet on foot by any againſt their Brother-Chriſtians; witneſs the general <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the diſperſion, baniſhment and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement of moſt, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Few or none re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, but ſuch as either do <hi>precariò vivere,</hi> ſubſiſt by the charitie and alms of pious, well-affected Chriſtians; or elſe, not ſtanding, forſooth, <hi>recti in curiâ,</hi> dare ſcarce bee known to bee in beeing) Might wee not juſtly fear the Cauſe would ſuffer by the very interpoſing of ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates? <hi>Away with ſuch fellows from the earth;</hi> 'tis mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, too great mercie that they live: <hi>Theſe fellows are but permitted to ſojourn here, and they will needs bee Lords.</hi> Could Prudence prompt them to bee Mediators, whoſe very intereſt carrieth a denial in the forehead? Wee would bee loth to have our Reaſon queſtioned, while wee would improve our Chriſtianitie. Good Cauſes wee have often known miſcarrie for want of fitting Inſtruments to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage them. Nor could wee wiſh our Enemie a greater miſchief, then for the obteining of his purpoſe to uſe unwelcom Mediators. Ther's as much truth in <hi>This,</hi> Hee teacheth to denie that asks <hi>amiſs,</hi> as is in <hi>That,</hi> That asks but <hi>faintly.</hi> And, in good ſadneſs, could wee hope for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by whatſoever wee could ſaie or do? Is not the very Name of <hi>Roial Partie</hi> an inexpiable crime? Is not the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word <hi>Malignant</hi> a rub and prejudice to the juſteſt ſuit? And is not this our caſe? or do wee ſtand on any better terms? Wee fear'd the leaſt appearance of our Name might bee interpreted ſom grand Deſign; and, inſtead of finde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſucceſs wee ſought, ſeal up the ſentence of His condemnation. Beſide; would it not intrench upon our Prudence, to irritate the ſpirit of an adverſarie, by the ill choice of Interceſſors? Nor have wee yet ſo far forgot our Reaſon, as to attempt the quenching of a Flame by the ſuffuſion of Oil. The unacceptableneſs of our perſons and Condition with the great Statiſts and Grandees, whoſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and reſpect of perſons diſcover's they have not much to do with God, give's the firſt Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165082:11"/>of good ſucceſs, and conſequently a Reaſon of our Non-appearing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> when wee reflect and caſt our eies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Managers of the late and preſent Agitations, wee think that Argument enough to ſtop our mouths, and patronize our Silence. Wee would not willingly incur the cenſure of ſpeaking to no purpoſe, to men reſolved and inflexible: to men whoſe Principles are to them as true, as they are falſ in themſelves: to men who preſume upon their own Dictats as infallible Oracles: who rear huge buildings upon ſandie grounds, and raiſe Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on none or moſt deceiving Premiſes<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: who, in the very Principles they ſomtime pretend to own (for ask their Presbyterian Brethren whether they could ever get them to ſtand to any) are as ſlipperie as Eels, as variable as the Moon, and conſtant onely in inconſtancie. Have they not juſtjfied their excentrick motions and higheſt irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities with the decried Principles of ſpecial Providence and Impulſes of the Spirit? Have they not own'd and practis'd the Aſſertion, that Faith is not to bee kept with Enemies? And, on that ſcore, abus'd the <hi>wiſeſt Head in Chriſtendom?</hi> Not keeping faith with any, God or Man? Have they not perverted Holie Scripture, and the heroick actions of ſom Saints, aſſiſted by immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at inſpiration, to authorize the higheſt villanies? And are wee ſtill to learn the fetches of Sathan? or can wee bee ignorant of their devices? <hi>Quo teneam nodo?</hi> If wee could yet but gueſs what lock to have them at, what weapon to fight with, perhaps they would not ſeem ſo wiſe, not ſo invincible. But, indeed, it is no matter for the <hi>Means,</hi> they are reſolved on the <hi>End, per fas, per nefus;</hi> and, rather then miſcarrie or come ſhort of their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Defigns, run madly upon the pretended unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able crimes of thoſe truly Honorable and worthie Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, who formerly ſate at the helm, and managed the great affairs in Church and State: And, (that wee may throughly know the meaning of their Canting-language, <hi>Pro REGE, Pro Parliamento, Pro Religione,</hi> and I know
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165082:11"/>not what) nothing now conducing to their Ends, though never ſo much decried by themſelvs and ſpoke againſt in others, muſt bee omitted for the puniſhment of a fooliſh people flatter'd into miſerie; and for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of an <hi>Abſolute, Independent and Arbitrarie Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, over the Fortunes, Lives and Conſciences of their late fellow-ſubjects, now their vaſſals; who, of the most Free people in the world, under a pretence of Libertie are cheated into Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> far worſe then the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Brick-kilns, or the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Argire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having ſuch as theſe to deal withall, <hi>Quibus non perſuadebis etiamſi perſuaſeris,</hi> had not our Application been in vain, much like the waſhing of an Aethiop? <hi>Can a Leopard change his ſpots, or a Black-More his skin? Then,</hi> ſaith the infallible Oracle that cannot lie, <hi>may they that are accuſtomed to do evil learn to do well.</hi> Believ it, SIR, the graſping at a Crown was not to bee diſſvaded by our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; and that deſtructive Principle alone which drive's them on <hi>(Of a pretended ſpecial Call from heaven)</hi> outvies with them the higheſt Demonſtrations of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Law, or Religion. To which if wee ſhall add (what wee conceiv the Truth, and the ground of theſe Preſumptions) the Real, not Imaginarie Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, which, queſtionleſs, lie heavie on their ſouls, and egg them on, <hi>Scelera ſceleribus tueri,</hi> to fortifie and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein what they have don; as doubting of the iſſue of their former ſins, but by attempting greater; you will bee ſoon induced to believ, that, as their reſolution was to ſtop their ears againſt the voice of the Charmer, charm hee never ſo wiſely; ſo, all our words and arguments had been no better then <hi>Sibyllae folia,</hi> the ſport of the windes, or the barking of a dog againſt the Moon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In which opinion wee have the greater cauſ to bee confirmed, when wee call to minde the fruitleſneſs and non-ſucceſs of thoſe many Applications, which have been made to theſe great Maſters of the world, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſom of the Antient, Orthodox and Legal Clergie, but alſo by many of the Presbyterian perſuaſion; who,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165082:12"/>though we cannot excuſe their too great activitie in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting theſe unnatural diſtempers by their compliance and encouragement, have yet, though like very ill Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, after ſuch Premiſes as they laid themſelvs, which were neceſſarily productive of theſe horrid conſequences, utterly denied the Concluſion, and flung the dirt of this deteſtable action in the face of their ſomtime Brethren, now cruel perſecuting Enemies.</p>
            <p>Wee have read indeed, SIR, the Vindications, which have com forth from ſom particular Members, and from ſom Bodies (or, as they love to ſpeak, ſom Claſſes) of them. Wee cannot but approve and ſaie Amen to their abhorrence of ſo traiterous an Attempt. But when wee weigh the grounds they go upon; <hi>their voluntarie Oaths and Covenants,</hi> of which wee may well ask, <hi>Quis requiſivit?</hi> What Law of God or Man required them? When wee remember not a word or argument urged by them from their former <hi>Legal Oath of Allegiance</hi> to their Undoubted Sovereign; as if there had been no tie or obligation upon their Souls, till that accurſed thing, <hi>the Covenant,</hi> came out to the diſturbance of Three Kingdoms: When wee conſider that their chiefeſt Motives are drawn from their <hi>Implicit Faith</hi> of the pretended (ſo they now appear) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, Proteſtations, and Declarations of <hi>the Gentlemen at Weſtminſter,</hi> to bee very tender of the Rights, Honor, and Life of their Sovereign, and to make Him <hi>a Glorious King;</hi> and ſo indeed they have, <hi>by Suffering:</hi> when wee reflect upon the Riſe and grounds firſt laid and ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in by them, which infallibly begat that fatal ſtroke, which was given immediatly, indeed, by other hands, but conſequentially by theirs: (For, if it bee reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in point of Law, that there are no Acceſſories, but all are Principals in high Treaſon, no queſtion they have as much to anſwer for, that bound the Hands, as they that cut off the Head of His Sacred Majeſtie) When wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe and many more, which highly aggravate their guilt, wee cannot think them ſo innocent and free from participation in that horrid crime of ſhedding the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165082:12"/>blood of our Bleſſed Sovereign, but that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinitely beholden to the Pardon and Praiers of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Charitie, <hi>That God would not impute His blood to them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to convince them, what need they have of Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>blood, to waſh their ſouls from the guilt of ſhedding His.</hi> In confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the efficacie of which praier, as wee hope they will at laſt perceive their Error, and upon ſight thereof bee pricked at the hearts, and bring forth the worthie fruits of Penance, ſo wee ſhall with a willing minde imitate the Father of the Prodigal, bee readie to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein them with the embraces of peace, and to ſalute them with the holie kiſs of Charitie.</p>
            <p>In the interim, the cold or no-reception of them, who had gon ſo far along with theſe Uſurpers, was ſuch a cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-card, ſo poor an encouragement to us, who are look'd upon as altogether <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and wholly oppoſite to their deſtructive Grounds, Waie, and End, that wee thought it wiſdom to ſit down and weep by theſe waters of Babylon, as deſpairing of any ſutable entertainment, or probabilitie of good ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, when, being lately warned that the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice offered in the Humble Addreſs of our Reverend and Learned Brother was either not accepted or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, wee had too great reaſon to conclude, that the light of Nature beeing wholly extinguiſhed, and the Bowels of Chriſtian Charitie (as their Brother <hi>Judas</hi>'s) guſhed out, all further Counſels or ghoſtlie admonitions would bee but giving <hi>Holie things to Dogs,</hi> or caſting <hi>Pearls to Swine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, SIR, wee have at laſt diſcharg'd our thoughts into your charitable boſom: and hope that one or all of theſe will ſet us right in the good opinion of all Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous honeſt men. Yet as wee cannot but acknowledg with all thankfulneſs your great favour and tender reſpect in the communication of your fears, leſt our honor or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhould bee thought to lie too open to the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable deſcants of cenſorious and ill-affected men, ſo we muſt ever think our ſelvs bound to your goodneſs, as for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165082:13"/>your own charitable conſtruction of us, ſo for giving us this opportunitie of diſcovering our ſenſe and judgment: which as wee have hitherto, <hi>cum bono Deo,</hi> atteſted by our Sufferings, and ſtill ſhall, God aſſiſting us, with our Lives, and, which is dearer to us, with our Souls, ſo wee truſt this free and publick Declaration will for the future preclude and ſtop up the way of all uncharitable ſurmiſes, and confront the leaſt ſuſpitions of our appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and compliance; and confirm in you a fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction not onely of our Profeſſion but of our Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; which, wee beſeech you to believ, wee are ſo far from thinking much of, or repining at, that, on the contrarie, wee cannot but rejoice and triumph in them as our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honor and our Crown; <hi>eſteeming the reproaches of Chriſt greater riches then the threaſures of this world;</hi> and glorying with the Apoſtles <hi>that wee were counted worthie to ſuffer for His Name,</hi> in the Profeſſion of our Faith, Dutie and Allegiance to the <hi>Best of Kings,</hi> our late moſt Dear and glorious Sovereign, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> CHARLS the MARTYR.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nomen Ejus in benedictionibus.</l>
               <l>Uſque quò, Domine, uſque quò!</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="epigraph">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:165082:13"/>
            <head>TERTULLIANUS.</head>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtianus nullius eſt hoſtis, nedum Imperatoris: quem ſciens à Deo ſuo conſtitui, neceſſe est ut &amp; ipſum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat &amp; revereatur &amp; honoret &amp; ſalvum velit. — Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus ergo Imperatorem ſic, quomodo &amp; nobis licet, &amp; ipſi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit, ut hominem à Deo ſecundum; &amp; quicquid eſt, à Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem. Hoc &amp; Ipſe volet. Sic enim omnibus major est, dum ſolo vero Deo minor eſt. Sic &amp; ipſis Diis major eſt, dum &amp; ipſi in poteſtate ſunt Ejus. Itaque &amp; ſacrificamus pro ſalute Imperatoris, ſed Deo noſtro &amp; Ipſius; ſed quomodo praecepit Deus, purâ prece. <hi>ad Scapulam, parag. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nos pro ſalute Imperatoris Deum invocamus aeternum, Deum verum, Deum vivum; quem &amp; Ipſi Imperatores propitium ſibi praeter caeteros malunt: ſciunt quis Illis dederit Imperium; ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt quâ homines, quis &amp; animam. Sentiunt eum eſſe Deum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, in cujus ſolius potestate ſunt; à quo ſunt ſecundi, poſt quem primi, ante omnes &amp; ſuper omnes Deos. — Illius &amp; Ipſe, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus &amp; coelum &amp; omnis creatura. Indè eſt Imperator, unde &amp; homo antè quàm Imperator: indè poteſtas Illi, unde &amp; ſpiritus. Illuc ſuſpicientes Chriſtiani, manibus expanſis, quia innocuis; capite nudo, quia non erubeſcimus; denique ſine monitore, quia de pectore, oramus pro omnibus Imperatoribus, vitam Illis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixam, Imperium ſecurum, Domum tutam, Exercitus fortes, Senatum fidelem, Populum probum, Orbem quietum, &amp; quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque hominis &amp; Caeſaris vota ſunt.</p>
               <p>Hoc agite boni Praeſides, extorquete animam Deo ſupplican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem pro Imperatore. </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Apol. parag. 30.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
